Guide to the Carl F. Schreiber Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings and research projects, circa 1910-1957; Series II; (10 boxes)
  - Harro Harring: research materials, correspondence, thesis.
    - Harro Harring: documentary materials
      - "Schäfer, Berichte aus Paris, after returning from London 26 Nov. 1838 and 6 Dez. 1839 [folder title]." (Box 6)
        This folder contains a series of transcribed reports headed "Beilage zum Bericht Noés aus Mainz vom [various dates], followed by a series number and a dateline from Paris, generally a few days earlier than the Mainz date. Typed and in a German hand, ca. 77 leaves. With an ALS from Fritz Antonius to Schreiber ("Herr Professor"), Vienna, 20 March 1929 describing his work on these materials.
    - Harro Harring: secondary literature
      - "Erzählendes." Transcripts of contemporary notices and reviews of Harring's fiction, in Schreiber's and another American hand, 12 leaves. (Box 6)
      - [Gelzer, Heinrich] Die geheimen deutschen Verbindungen in der Schweiz sein 1833 (Basel, 1847). Typed excerpts with annotation in Schreiber's hand. (Box 6)
        Other excerpts in the folder, presumably from the same book, include "Die Religion der Zukunft," 1 p.; "Herwegh und Follen," 2 pages, typed, annotated by Schreiber; "Freiligrath und die Tendenz," 1 leaf; and 20 leaves of handwritten excerpts (and notes?).
      - Marr, Wilhelm. Das junge Deutschland in der Schweitz (1846). Typed excerpts annotated in Schreiber's hand, 14 leaves. (Box 6)
      - Sass, Johann. "Zur Lebensgeschichte Harro Harrings." Sonderdruck aus "Die Heimat." (marked "Okt. 27"), 4 p. (Box 6)
      - Schreiber, Carl F. Two chapters of his dissertation on Harring (in German)., 2 (Box 6)
        The first chapter is an account of Harring's life through 1832. The second is entitled "Polen." The typescripts appear to be from different drafts (the orthography differs—in the second chapter, nouns are not capitalized.) Chapter I: 13 leaves; "Polen": 28 leaves. Both with handwritten changes.
      - Schweizer, Paul. Geschichte der schweizerischen Neutralitaet. (Zürich, 1895). Typed excerpt, 29 leaves. (Box 6)
        One leaf is handwritten and may belong in "Mémoires sur la Jeune Italie.. ."
    - Harro Harring: miscellaneous
      - "Allgemein Politisches [folder title]." (Box 6)
        Contains typed and handwritten notes and excerpts from various sources, some contemporary with Harring, 12 leaves.
      - "Harring, Harro, Allgemeines [folder heading]." (Box 6)
        Contains an assortment of notes and excerpts on various German literary figures, partly typed, partly in Schreiber's hand.
      - La giovine Italia... 1o Trimestre – 1o Fascicolo. Marsiglia, 1832. [16] p., original wrappers. (Box 6)
      - "Das junge Deutschland [folder title]." (Box 6)
        This folder contains the following material: Two blue notebooks, in Schreiber's hand, with titles "Das revolutionäre Europa im Spiegel d. deut. Lit. (1817-1848)" and "Revolution II. Vortrag."; Typed outline, "Das junge Deutschland. May 31, 1930," l leaf, with a page of bibliography.; Typed transcription of a letter from Carlyle to Rev. W. Jacobson, 23 Aug. 1840, concerning Mazzini.
      - Littlefield, Walter. Review of Mazzini: Prophet of Modern Europe, by Gwilym O. Griffith (NY: Harcourt, Brace). Clipping from The New York Times Book Review., 1933 January 22 (Box 6)
      - "Philhellenismus – Allgemeines [folder title]." Assorted notes, typed and handwritten, on this topic, including bibliography and excerpts from secondary literature. (Box 6)
      - Negative photostats from the British Library and the New York Public Library (Box 6)
    - Schreiber's correspondence
      The following correspondence relates to Schreiber's research on Harro Harring and is in roughly chronological order.
      - Harring, Therese. ALS, APCS, autograph poem, and clipping., 1910-1912 (Box 6)
        Therese Harring was the Niece of Harro Harring.
      - American Express Company. TLS, concerning archival records from Jersey, Channel Islands, 1928 February 20 (Box 6)
      - Houben, H.H. TLS, Harring material in Berlin Staatsarchiv, 1928 July 24 (Box 6)
      - Frankenburg, Richard. ALS, 1928 July 25 (Box 6)
      - British Museum, TLS, response to reference query, 1928 August 12 (Box 6)
      - Sass, Johann. APCS. Berlin, New Year's greeting, 1928 December 29 (Box 6)
      - Elliott, Maud Howe, TLS to Schreiber. Palm Beach, FL, 31 Jan. 1935, 1 leaf, with his reply, TL (copy) [New Haven] 6 Feb. 1935., circa 1935; 2 (Box 6)
        The exchange has to do with Schreiber's efforts to establish that Mrs. Elliot's uncle, Sam Ward, was the same as the one married to Meodora Ward, to whom the American edition of Dolores was dedicated. With typed transcript of a letter from Harring to Mrs. Ward, New York, 5 March 1846, 2 leaves. Related to the following folder:
      - "Harro Harring vs. Harper Bros. [folder heading].", circa 1935 (Box 6)
        Correspondence and other notes relating to Schreiber's attempt to find the records of the 1846 lawsuit between Harring and Harper Bros. concerning the novel Dolores. Also correspondence relating to Schreiber's attempt to identify Meodora Ward, to whom the novel is dedicated. With apparently unrelated correspondence asking various U.S. libraries about their holdings in titles by Harring.
      - Pauls, V. 2 TLS to Schreiber. Kiel, 30 April and 25 July 1929, 4 p. stamped "Schlesw.-Holstein. Landesbibliothek"), with typed list, "Verzeichnis der Manuskripte Harro Harrings in der Schleswig-Holsteinischen Landesbibliothek, Kiel, compiled by Dr. [Richard] Frankenberg, 2 p. (carbon copy)., circa 1929 (Box 6)
        Schreiber was to send back a copy of the list indicating which manuscripts he wished to have transcribed. With copies of Schreiber's letters to Pauls, 29 Jan., 16 April, and 27 May 1929.
      - Pauls, V. TLS to Schreiber. Kiel, 29 March 1939. 2 p., letter head of the Gesellschaft für Schleswig-Holsteinische Geschichte., circa 1939 (Box 6)
        Inquires about the progress of Schreiber's Harring research. Notes that Dr. Frankenberg has been drawn away from his research by other responsibilities, but is now in a position to work on Harring again.
      - Bülck, Rudolf. TLS to Schreiber. Kiel, 8 Sept. 1948, 1 p., circa 1948 (Box 6)
        Asks for Schreiber's advice about a Harring letter owned by Wilhelm Ladewig, subsequently published by Ladewig as "Harro Harrings Brief aus Cowes of Wright vom 23. Mai 1848" in Jb. des Nordfriesischen Instituts, Jg. 1 (1949). Bülck identifies himself as Bibliotheksrat at the university library in Kiel.
      - Ladewig, Wilhelm. 2 TLS to Schreiber. Dörpling, 4 and 9 Oct. 1948, 2 p., circa 1948 (Box 6)
        Sends two articles, offers to collaborate. The second letter encloses a list, "Material über Harro Harring im Besitz von Wilhelm Ladewig," 1 leaf. The letters refer to earlier correspondence.
      - Glaser, Hermann. 2 TLS to Schreiber. Nürnberg, undated and 6 Nov. 1951. With Schreiber's responses, 31 Oct. 1951 and 27 Jan.1952., circa 1951-1952 (Box 6)
        The correspondence relates to Schreiber's article "Hamlet ist Deutschland," (PMLA, 1913) but includes an account of his career and why he wrote no more about Harro Harring (intervention of the First World War, lack of time afterwards).
    - Two large glass negatives (Box 6)
      These negatives showing (1) portraits of Harring, Maltits, Heine, and Börne and (2) another portrait (of Harring in old age?).
    - Schreiber, assorted notes, autograph and typed, on half sheets (Box 6)
  - Fiction and Fantasy, 1927, circa 1927 (Box 7)
    Drafts and paste-ups for the book Fiction and fantasy of German romance; Selections from the German Romantic authors, 1790-1830, in English translation, edited by Frederick E. Pierce... and Carl F. Schreiber (New York, etc.: Oxford University Press, 1927.
  - Speck portfolio, 1932, circa 1932; 48 (Box 8)
    Goetheana. A centenary portfolio of forty-three facsimiles and reproductions of unique or rare items from the William A Speck collection of Goetheana (Yale University Press, 1932). Included are typescript and proofs, production figures and costs, advertising prospectuses, reviews, correspondence, reactions and alternate cover mock-ups and set of facsimiles.
  - Minimum German, 1935, circa 1935 (Box 9)
    Correspondence and documents relating to the book Minimum German by Schreiber and Nils G. Sahlin (New York: F. S. Crofts & Co, 1935)
  - Speck catalog, 1940. Goethe's Works with the Exception of Faust(Yale University Press, 1940), circa 1940
    - Volume I
      - Drafts of Schreiber's introduction (Box 9)
      - Production of the facsimiles: plans, lists, documents from Albert Frisch Verlag, Berlin (Box 9)
      - Production with the Yale University Press: plans, correspondence, samples, etc., 2 (Box 9)
      - Suggestions by Alfred Bergmann (Box 9)
        Alfred Bergmann had just re-edited the Kippenberg Goethe catalog.
      - Financial documents & complimentary copies (Box 9)
      - Reprint of Speck biography (Box 9)
      - Reviews (Box 9)
    - Volume II (Faust): Plans, correspondence, etc. including letters relating to Vera Lachmann's proposed work on the project (Box 9)
    - Volume III: Card index relating to proposed contents (Box 9)
  - The "Chicago" Goethe, 1948-57, circa 1948-1957
    - Contracts and correspondence: Schreiber, Victor Lange, Arnold E. Bergraesser, University of Chicago Press, Henry Regnery Company, Heinz Blum, Frederick von Schleinitz, James Babb, etc., 2 (Box 10)
    - Goethe. Novelle., 6 (Box 10)
      Typescript translation by Schreiber, in many copies, with suggested changes by several persons
    - Goethe. The Campaign in France 1792. (Box 10)
      Translated by Jane Bannard Greene and Heinz Norden.
    - Goethe. Dichtung und Wahrheit., 4 (Box 10)
      Translated by Minna Steele Smith with revisions by Schreiber, Wallace J. Williamson, and Jane Bannard Greene. With a folder of contracts, readers' reports, and correspondence
    - Goethe. Dichtung und Wahrheit., 18 (Box 11)
    - Goethe. Faust I. (Box 11)
      Unidentified, incomplete translation, in an unidentified hand and typed
    - Goethe. Götz von Berlichingen. (Box 11)
      Various corrected typescripts, Act 1 only
  - Edgar Allan Poe
    - Schreiber. "A close-up of Poe." Saturday Review of Literature 3:11 (1926), printed version (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "Mr Poe at his conjurations again." The Colophon," 1930. Drafts and printed version (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "Poe and Goethe." Typescript (related textually to above); another typescript filed with the "Goethe in America" project (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "Mr. Poe gets up books." Typescripts (Box 12)
    - [Schreiber?]"Poe Flurries." Incomplete typescript (Box 12)
    - [Schreiber?] [Essay on Poe]. Typescript (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "Poe works in periodicals." Typescript (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "Henry Beck Hirst." Drafts, typescript (Box 12)
    - Schreiber. "A few works on etiquette." Typed notes (for a lecture?) (Box 12)
    - Federmann, Arnold. "Johann Heinrich Füssli und Edgar Allan Poe." Typescript (Box 12)
    - Correspondence relating to Poe (Box 12)
- Writings by others, circa 1930s; Series III; (2 boxes)
  - Yale graduate student papers from the 1930s. Typescripts, unless otherwise noted., circa 1930s; 2 (Box 13)
    These folders contain the following papers: Blume, Albert M. K. (Ph.D. 1940). "First English translation in America of Goethe's 'Götz von Berlichingen,'" 1934; Eastman, Anthony Dey (Ph.D. 1935). "Goethe and the French Revolution," 20 April 1932; Gemeinhardt, Lawrence (Ph.D. 1940). "Goethe and Werther after 1774"; Hanrahan, William R., Jr. (MA, 1942). "The effects of Goethe's Werther in England"; Hegeman, Daniel V. B. (Ph.D, 1934). Dissertation defense, autograph ms., with questions in Schreiber's hand. The dissertation was entitled "The Cultural Background of Classical Weimar Studies in the Modenjournal of Bertuch and Kraus, 1786- 1806"; McKenzie, Earl D (Ph.D. 1935). "The problem of the pseudo-Goethean poem 'Joseph,'" 15 June 1934; Scholz, Albert (Ph.D., 1942). "Sturm und Drang in 'Götz von Berlichingen,'" 13 June 1934; Tiller, Fritz (Ph.D, 1940). "Faust und Werther als die beiden Pols des Sturms und Drangs," June 1934; Zerner, Marianne (Ph.D. 1939). "Ueber die Entstehungsgeschichte des Urfausts".
  - Goethe in America
    - Correspondence, plans and outlines (Box 13)
      Articles in typescript, some with correspondence:
    - Church, Howard W, "Henry Irving's Faust in America" (Box 13)
    - Eastburn, Iola Kay. "Whittier and Goethe" (Box 13)
    - Heller, Clarence Nevin. "The Goethean Literary Society of Franklin and Marshall College" (Box 13)
    - Kelley, John A. "Musical settings of Goethe's poems by American composers" (Box 13)
    - Ladd, Benjamin F., and Adolph B. Benson. "Goethe biography in America", 2 (Box 13)
    - Lehnert, Frederick O., and Adolph B. Benson. "Percival and Goethe" (Box 13)
    - Leyen, Friedrich von der. "Goethe and world literature" (Box 13)
    - Long, Orie William. "Werther in America" (Box 14)
    - Raschen, J. F. L. "Lewis Morrison and his 'Faust' production in America" (Box 14)
    - _____. "Emerson and Goethe" (Box 14)
    - Rose, William. [correspondence only] (Box 14)
    - Schreiber, Carl F. "Poe and Goethe" (Box 14)
    - Schwarze, William Nathaniel. "Goethe's contacts with the Moravian Church" (Box 14)
    - Selmer, Carl. "Goethe celebrations in America" (Box 14)
    - Shelley, Philip A. "Goethe in the American annuals and gift-books" (Box 14)
    - Voss, Ernst. "Goethe monuments in America" (Box 14)
    - Wadepuhl, Walter. "Goethe's interest in the New World"`, 2 (Box 14)
    - Zeydel, Edwin H. "Translations of Goethe's works in America" (Box 14)
  - Papers by colleagues in the field. Typescripts (Box 14)
    This folder contains the following papers: Anon. "The first translation of Werther."; Aron, Willi. "The mature Goethe and Rousseau"; Curtius, Ernst Robert. "Goethes Aktenführung." Signed offprint; Morente. "Goethe und die hispanische Welt"; Reinsch, F. J. "Problems in current Goethe research"; Spann, Meno. "Mephistopheles (ante spectators)"; Trevelyan, Humphrey. "Goethe as thinker," with corresp. ca. 1936; Wadepuhl, Walter. "Amerika, du hast es besser".